Guide to the Clair Leonard Papers, approximately 1926-1962
Vassar College Libraries Archives and Special Collections
Clair Leonard Papers
circa 1925-1962
Leonard, Clair, 1901-1963
2.5 cubic feet (9 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, music scores, manuscript, typescripts, audio tape, biographical materials, concert programs, and clippings relating to the life and professional career of Clair Leonard.
Biographical Note
Clair Leonard was born in 1901. A noted composer and teacher, Leonard studied at Harvard, the Ecole Normale de Musique in Paris, and the New England Conservatory and with Nadia Boulanger of Paris. In 1934, after teaching music and French at Harvard, Radcliffe, and the Univerity of Vermont, Leonard joined the Music Department of Vassar College, where he taught as an assisstant and associate professor until 1947. He then moved to Bard College, serving there as professor of music and chair of the music department until 1963. Leonard composed a wide variety of music, ranging from musical theater to pieces for small ensembles and orchestral and choral works. One of his most notable compositions was music to accompany W. H. Auden's one-act play, The Dance of Death. Clair Leonard died in Poughkeepsie, NY, on February 7, 1963.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes correspondence regarding mainly the performance and publication of Clair Leonard's compositions; copies of music scores; an audio tape of a performance of "Song of the Universal"; biographical materials compiled by Clair Leonard; a typescript of It Can't Happen Here by John C. Moffitt and Sinclair Lewis; a typescript of The Natural Man by Theordore Browne; a typescript of The Principles of Right Reason by Howard S. Leonard; programs of concert performances by Clair Leonard and/or of his music; and clippings concerning concert performances of his music.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Browne, Theodore, 1910-; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951; Moffitt, John C., 1901-1969; Rascher, Sigurd
Organizations:
Bard College--Faculty; Vassar College. Department of Music; Vassar College--Faculty
Subjects:
Composers--United States--20th century
Document Types:
Scores (documents for music)
VCL Categories
Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, December 2013
Acquisition Information
Collection transferred from the Vassar College Department of Music (M2010-008).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The audio tape in Series III will need to be duplicated at the researcher's expense before use.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 3 series: Correspondence, Scores, and Miscellaneous Materials.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1936-1962
  This series consists mainly of Clair Leonard'a correspondence with music publishers and concert venues. Also included is some personal correspondence. The series in arranged chronologically.
- Series II. Scores, circa 1926-1961
  This series consists of copies of Clair Leonard's musical scores. These include manuscripts, prints, blueprints, and photocopies. The series is arranged alphabetically.
- Series III. Miscellaneous Materials, circa 1936-1961
  This series includes audio tape, typescripts, concert programs, biographical materials, and clippings. The series is arranged alphabetically.
Container List
- SERIES I. Correspondence, 1936-1962
  - 1936-1937 (Folder 1.1)
  - 1944-1948 (Folder 1.2)
  - 1953-1955 (Folder 1.3)
  - 1961-1962 (Folder 1.4)
- SERIES II. Scores, circa 1926-1962
  - Ballad of the Successful Young man, undated (Folder 2.1)
  - Capriccio for Woodwind Quintet "Kappa Ta Lamb da, undated (Folders 2.2-2.3)
  - Choral Vocalise No. 2, circa 1961 (Folder 2.4)
  - [Collection: If I Speak with the Tongues of Men, The Earth is the Lord's, Canyon Voyage, Rondo Cappriccio for Oboe and Piano], circa 1945-circa 1949 (Folder 2.5)
  - Concerto for Piano Forte and Orchestra, B flat minor, 1933 (Folders 2.6-2.9)
  - Cor Mio (Monteverdi, arr. Leonard), undated (Folder 2.10)
  - Dreated He Them, undated (Folder 2.11)
  - A Dance, undated (Folder 2.12)
  - Dance of Death, 1935 (Folders 2.13-15)
  - Dance of Death, 1935 (Folders 3.1-3.8)
  - Dance of Death, 1935 (Folders 7.1-7.4)
  - Elegiac Rhapsody, 1961 (Folder 1.8)
  - An Elegy for Spain, 1937 (Folder 7.5)
  - Exercises in Sight Singing and Dictation, undated (Folder 1.9)
  - Four Piano Sonatas, 1931 (Folder 3.9)
  - The Grandsons, 1943 (Folder 3.10)
  - Hommage à Ravel, undated (Folder 4.1)
  - Hungarian Folksongs, 1957 (Folder 4.2)
  - [Incidental music to plays at Bard College and Vassar College], 1934-1959 (Folder 4.3)
  - [Isolated pencil sketches], undated (Folder 4.4)
  - Komm susser Tod-chorale, after 1945 (Folder 7.6)
  - Missa Sancti Albani, 1940 (Folder 4.5)
  - [Music for dance and for films], circa 1952-circa 1957 (Folder 4.6)
  - My Country Right or Left, 1935 (Folder 4.7)
  - [Organ music-Six Versets on "O Quanta Qualia"], 1955 (Folder 4.8)
  - Peace on Earth-a Christmas Cantata, undated (Folder 4.9)
  - The Price of Wisdom, undated (Folder 4.10)
  - Psalm 42, undated (Folder 4.11)
  - Psalm 121, circa 1947 (Folder 4.12)
  - Psalm fo O.J.J., 1930 (Folder 7.7)
  - Recitative and Abracadabra, 1941; Includes correspondence between Clair Leonard and Sigurd M. Rascher (Folder 4.13)
  - Requiem, 1944 (Folders 5.1-5.2)
  - [Secular songs], circa 1926-circa 1960 (Folder 5.3)
  - [Short pieces of chamber groups], 1955-1957 (Folder 5.4)
  - [Short sacred choruses], undated (Folder 5.5)
  - [Short secular choruses], circa 1929-circa 1960 (Folder 5.6)
  - Sinfonetta for Men's Voices (Psalm 130), undated (Folder 5.7)
  - Sonata for Violin and Piano, 1940 (Folder 5.8)
  - Song of the Universal, 1940; Folders 1-2 of 7 (Folders 5.9-5.10)
  - Song of the Universal, 1940; Folders 3-4 of 7 (Folders 1.10-1.11)
  - Song of the Universal, 1940; Folders 5-7 of 7 (Folders 7.8-7.10)
  - [Songs (light), parodies, isolated pieces from show music, etc.], undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Folder 6.1)
  - [Songs (light), parodies, isolated pieces from show music, etc.], Folder 2 of 2 (Folder 7.11)
  - Sun Dance, undated (Folder 6.2)
  - Symphony, undated (Folder 6.3)
  - Te Deum, circa 1945 (Folder 6.4)
  - Tombeaux, 1929; Folder 1 of 2 (Folder 6.5)
  - Tombeaux, 1929; Folder 2 of 2 (Folder 7.12)
  - Tonight We Correlate, circa 1937 (Folder 1.13)
  - Trio for Violin, Viola, and Cello for Boris Koutzen, undated (Folders 6.6-6.8)
  - [Vassar College Centennial music], circa 1960; Includes correspondence (Folder 6.9)
  - War Song of the Dinas Vawr, 1937 (Folder 6.10)
  - [Miscellaneous scores], undated (Folder 7.13)
  - [Scores not by Clair Leonard], undated (Folder 7.14)
- SERIES III. Miscellaneous Materials, circa 1930-circa 1962
  - Audio tape - Song of the Universal; Hayden, Sonata, B minor, undated (Box 8)
  - Biographical materials, after 1937 (Folder 8.1)
  - Clippings, circa 1936-circa 1960 (Folder 8.2)
  - It Can't Happen Here, by John C. Moffitt and Sinclair Lewis, 1936 (Folder 8.3)
  - The Natural Man, by Theodore Browne, circa 1936 (Folder 8.4)
  - Performance notes, undated (Folder 8.5)
  - The Principles of Right Reason, by Howard S. Leonard, 1953; Includes 13 p. of notes in hand of Clair Leonard (Folder 8.6)
  - Programs, circa 1934-1961; 6 folders. Includes program for performance of "America, America!" by Alfred Kreymborg with inscription by Kreymborg to Clair Leonard (folder 6). (Box 9)